A Guide to the Literary Fund Records of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1794-1869 (bulk 1811-1850)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Literary Fund Records of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1794-1869 (bulk 1811-1850)
The Library of Virginia
APA 146, APA 147, APA 148, APA 149, APA 150, APA 151, APA 152
3.87 cu. ft. (12 boxes and 6 volumes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Details of acquisition unknown.
Biographical Information
The Commonwealth of Virginia set aside money for public education for the first time in its history in 1811. The General assembly passed the bill that formally established the literary fund for education, first on January 24, 1810 in the House, and in the Senate February 8, 1810: "Be it enacted; that all escheats, confiscations, fines, penalties and forfeitures, and all rights in personal property accruing to the Commonwealth, as derelict, and having no rightful proprietor, be, and the same are hereby appropriated to the encouragement of learning. That the aforesaid fund shall be appropriated to the sole benefit of a school or schools, to be kept in each and every county within this Commonwealth." (House Journal, Feb. 2, 1810, Chap. 14, p. 15). Revenues derived from fines (except milita fines) and the sale of land escheated for unpaid taxes were deposited in the Literary fund and the money was used to build schools and educate the lower income children in the state.
As such, this allowed for the Second Auditor of the State Treasury, at the time James Brown Jr., to open an account with the Treasurer to be known as the Literary Fund to, "..be divided and appropriated as to the next legislature sees best adapted to the promotion of literature … Its direction is cast into the "Act to provide for the education of the Poor," in which is made a "solemn protest" against any future legislature's misapplying the Literary Fund to any other purpose than that of the education of the Poor. The President and the Directors of the Fund shall, as soon as sufficient funds be provided, establish schools for the education of the poor in each and every county and shall appoint an agent in every county to look after the returns to the fund and to prevent misappropriation." (Acts of Virginia Assembly, Feb. 12, 1811, Chap. 8, pp. 8-9. ).
The directors of the Literary Fund were formally designated to include the Governor, the Lieutenant Governor, Treasurer, Attorney General, and the President of Court of Appeals.
In 1818, the state legislature passed an act to appropriate a portion of the fund annually for the support of a state university (the University of Virginia) as well as for the education of the poor. (Acts of Virginia Assembly, Feb. 21, 1818, p. 14). Some of the other higher education institutions that received funding from the act were the Virginia Military Institute in Lexington, and the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond.The literary fund is still in existence today and provides services such as low-interest loans for school construction, grants under the interest rate subsidy program, debt service for technology funding, and support for the state’s share of teacher retirement required by the Standards of Quality.
Scope and Content
This is an artificial collection of multiple accessions from the Auditor of Public Accounts concerning the Virginia Literary Fund. The collection consists of seven (7) series of records housed in various boxes and volumes. The collection includes ledgers for fines, various receipts and vouchers (including for cash, bonds, surety debts, and other judgment). Given that the Literary Fund was financed by money from fines, land and property forfeitures, penalties, confiscations, escheats, and repayment of the debt for the War of 1812, this collection documents the financial histories of Virginians across various localities.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in the seven following Series:
Series I: Receipts and Vouchers, 1794-1851, 1854-1862, 1864 (APA 146)
Series II: Cash Receipts and Disbursements Ledger, 2 February 1810-21 June 1811, 4 July 1818-4 April 1821 (APA 147)
Series III: List of Lands Belonging or Escheated to the Commonwealth and Sold, 1814-1869 (APA 148)
Series IV: List of Lands Forfeited to the Literary Fund in 1816, ca. 1816 (APA 149)
Series V: Records of Cash Receipts, 1843-1847, 1850 (APA 150)
Series VI: List of Fines Returned as Insolvent, Not Found, Etc., 1820 (APA 151)
Series VII: Lists of Lands Vested in the President and Directors of the Literary Fund, 1832 (APA 152)
Contents List
- Series I: Receipts and Vouchers, 1794-1851, 1854-1862, 1864 (Accession APA 146)., 3.85 cu. ft. (11 boxes).
  This series consists primarily of vouchers for disbursements from the fund and receipts issued by the second auditor and treasurer. This series includes the following types of records: Second Auditor's Receipts, Treasurer's Receipts, Redemption of Land, Vouchers for Disbursements, and General Records.
  - General Records
    - Accounts and Vouchers, 1818. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Accounts and Vouchers, January, 1819. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Accounts and Vouchers, Jan-March, 1819. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Accounts, 1819. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Accounts, 1823-1824. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Affidavit, 1816. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Affidavit, 1864. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bonds for Escheated, 1822-1843. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Checks, 1829. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Certificates - James River and Kanawha Company, 1858. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Delinquent Muster Fines List, 1819. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fines - List, 1820-1859. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Memo of Bank Stock Held by the State (Bank of Virginia), undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Receipts - Auditors, 1824-1825. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Second Auditor's Receipts
    - Ma (Madison-Matthews Counties), 1823-1844. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Me-Mo (Mecklenburg-Monongalia Counties), 1823-1843. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mo-Na (Monroe-Nansemond Counties), 1823-1845. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ne-No (Nelson-Northampton Counties), 1823-1844. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - No-Pa (Northumberland-Patrick Counties), 1823-1844. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Pe-Pr (Pendleton-Prince Anne Counties), 1823-1844. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pr-Pu (Prince William-Pulaski Counties), 1823-1843. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Randolph County, 1825-1844. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Rappahannock County, 1825-1844. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Richmond County, 1824-1843. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Roanoke County, 1840-1844. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Rockbridge County, 1823-1843. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Rockingham County, 1823-1843. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Russell County, 1824-1844. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Scott County, 1823-1845. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Shenandoah County, 1823-1843. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Smyth County, 1832-1844. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Southampton County, 1823-1841. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Spotsylvania County (Fredericksburg), 1824-1845. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Stafford County, 1823-1844. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Surry County, 1823-1842. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sussex County, 1824-1844. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Tazewell County, 1824-1843. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Tyler County, 1823-1845. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Warren County, 1838-1843. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Warwick County, 1825-1840. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Washington County, 1823-1845. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Wayne County, 1843. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Westmoreland County, 1824-1844. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Wood County, 1824-1844. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Wythe County, 1823-1845. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - York County, 1824-1841. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Various Localities, 1823-1864. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Accomack-Augusta Counties, 1845-1848. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Barbour-Buckingham Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Cabell-Culpeper Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Danville-Essex Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Fairfax-Greensville Counties, 1845-1848. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Halifax-Jackson Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jefferson-Lynchburg Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Madison-Nottoway Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Ohio-Pulaski Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Randolph-Sussex Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Taylor-Wythe Counties, 1845-1849. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Accomack-Dinwiddie Counties, 1849-1851. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Fairfax-Middlesex Counties, 1849-1851. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Monongalia-Russell Counties, 1849-1851. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Scott-York Counties, 1849-1851. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Accomack-Wythe Counties, 1851-1852. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Various (Interest on Public Debt, Capitation Taxes), 1857-1861. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Accomack County, 1807-1822. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Albemarle County, 1810-1822. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Amelia County, 1810-1822. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Amherst County, 1811-1821. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Augusta County, 1806-1822. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bath County, 1806-1822. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bedford County, 1812-1823. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Berkley County, 1806-1822. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Botetourt County, 1805-1822. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Brooke County, 1807-1821. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Brunswick County, 1813-1823. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Buckingham County, 1801-1822. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Cabell County, 1811-1823. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Campbell County, 1807-1822. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Caroline County, 1806-1819. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Charles City County, 1812-1821. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Charlotte County, 1807-1822. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Chesterfield County, 1803-1822. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Culpeper County, 1797-1820. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Cumberland County, 1803-1822. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Dinwiddie County, 1819-1822. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth City County, 1822. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Essex County, 1803-1822. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Fairfax County, 1806-1822. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Fauquier County, 1803-1822. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Fluvanna County, 1812-1822. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Franklin County, 1809-1822. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Frederick County, 1806-1822. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Giles County, 1808-1822. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Gloucester County, 1807-1822. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Goochland County, 1810-1820. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Grayson County, 1810-1821. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Greenbrier County, 1799-1822. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Greensville County, 1810-1822. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Halifax County, 1805-1822. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Hanover County, 1817-1820. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Harrison County, 1807-1822. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Hampshire County, 1806-1823. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Hardy County, 1803-1823. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Henrico County, 1806-1822. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Henry County, 1810-1823. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Nansemond County, 1813-1823. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Nelson County, 1809-1820. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - New Kent County, 1800-1822. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Nicholas County, 1819-1822. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Norfolk County, 1810-1822. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Northampton County, 1804-1821. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Northumberland County, 1808-1822. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Nottoway County, 1805-1822. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Ohio County, 1811-1823. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Patrick County, 1812-1823. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Pendleton County, 1796-1823. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Pittsylvania County, 1810-1823. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Powhatan County, 1811-1822. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Preston County, 1820. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Prince Edward County, 1806-1821. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Prince George County, 1807-1822. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Prince William County, 1806-1822. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Princess Anne County, 1816-1822. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Randolph County, 1813-1822. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Richmond County, 1811-1822. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Rockbridge County, 1797-1823. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Rockingham County, 1803-1822. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Russell County, 1808-1823. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Scott County, 1817-1822. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Shenandoah County, 1803-1822. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Southampton County, 1811-1821. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Spotsylvania County, 1803-1821. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Stafford County, 1812-1822. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Surry County, 1805-1822. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Sussex County, 1812-1822. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Tazewell County, 1811-1823. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Tyler County, 1817-1823. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Warwick County, 1806-1821. (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Washington County, 1807-1822. (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Westmoreland County, 1807-1821. (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Wood County, 1803-1823. (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Wythe County, 1807-1823. (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - York County, 1814-1822. (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Various Localities, 1794-1801. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Various Localities, 1801-1809. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Various Localities, 1810-1823. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Various Localities, 1811-1822. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - City of Richmond, 1811-1822. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Stock Interest, 1813-1817. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Stock Interest, 1817-1820. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Stock Interest, 1820-1823. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Redemption of Land
    - Cabell County (West Virginia), 1820. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Randolph, 1816-1823. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Various Localities, 1816-1819. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Various Localities, 1817-1818. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Various Localities, 1819-1823. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Vouchers for Disbursement
    This subseries arranged chronologically.
    - Thomas Jefferson (University of Virginia), 1821-1822. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1819. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - January-February, 1820 (1 of 2). (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - January-February, 1820 (2 of 2). (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - July, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - August, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - September, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - October, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - November, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - December, 1821. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - January, 1822. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - February 1-5, 1822. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - February 6-14, 1822. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - February 15-23, 1822. (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Series II: Cash Receipts and Disbursements Ledger, 2 February 1810-21 June 1811, 4 July 1818-4 April 1821 (Accession APA 147)., Extent: 1 volume (1 box).
  This volume contains a variety of accounts as part of the ledger: list of cash receipts for the Literary Fund; accounts with school commissioners; other receipts, and disbursements ranging from February 1810 to April of 1821.
- Series III: Literary Fund List of Lands Belonging or Escheated to the Commonwealth and Sold 1814-1869 (Accession APA 148)., 1 volume
  This volume contains names of landowners, quantities, and locations of land, when sold, and for what price, and to whom.
- Series IV: List of Lands Forfeited to the Literary Fund in 1816 ca. 1816(Accession APA 149)., 1 volume
  This volume contains names of taxpayers, quantity of land, amounts of taxes due, and for which years delinquent. Includes only the following counties: Bath, Grayson, Greenbrier, Lee, Lewis, Randolph, Russell, Scott, Tazewell, and Wythe.
- Series V: Literary Fund Records of Cash Receipts 1843-1847;1850 (Accession APA 150)., 2 in. (1 box).
  This series consists primarily of vouchers for disbursements from the fund and receipts issued by the second auditor and treasurer. This series consists of the following types of records: Second Auditor's Receipts, Treasurer's Receipts, Redemption of Land, Vouchers for Disbursements, and General Records.
  - Notices for Judgments
    - 1843-1844. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1845-1847. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - June, 1849. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - A-C, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - D-L, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - M-W, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Literary Fund. Fines Returned as Insolvent, Not Found, Etc. List, 1820 (Accession APA 151)., 1 volume
  This volume contains the names of delinquent taxpayers, amounts owed, and dates of executions of court orders by sheriff.
- Series VII: List of Lands Vested in the President and Directors of the Literary Fund, 1832 (Accession APA 152)., 1 volume
  This volume contains lists of land in Grayson, Greenbrier, Lee, Mason, Monroe, Randolph, Scott, Tazewell, Wood, and Wythe counties. Lists include names of landowners, numbers of acres, years for which delinquent, amounts of taxes owed, and remarks.